<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en_UK"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://auxilia.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://auxilia.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en_UK" /><updated>2025-10-07T15:19:48+03:00</updated><id>https://auxilia.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Auxilia</title><subtitle>Design is thinking made visual.</subtitle><author><name>Joshua M.</name></author><entry><title type="html">A New Adventure…</title><link href="https://auxilia.io/articles/a-new-adventure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A New Adventure…" /><published>2025-07-16T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-16T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://auxilia.io/articles/a-new-adventure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://auxilia.io/articles/a-new-adventure/"><![CDATA[<p>Collective Rising seeks to (re)connect emerging leaders across East Africa with their purpose, with the communities they serve, and with each other. This initiative builds on my experiences and observations from decades of supporting nonprofit organizations around the world and, most recently, six years supporting the Regional Education Learning Initiative- RELI Africa to evolve into a leading voice on quality, inclusive education in East Africa. While I will continue supporting RELI Africa as a Senior Advisor, I hope Collective Rising will go further in exploring one key question: </p>

<p>“What might it look like to better support emerging leaders in East Africa to bring about transformational change with and for the communities they serve?” </p>

<p>This question feels particularly relevant considering this year’s United Nations General Assembly #UNGA78 where we marked the half-way point in the implementation of the Sustainable Development Goals with the SDG Summit. It is clear we still have a lot of work to do, particularly in the realm of transforming education and realizing #SDG4. I won’t claim to have all the answers, but I do believe that if we are committed to escaping the cycle of “business as usual,” we need more civil society leaders practicing leadership that is collective and interdependent rather than individualistic and hierarchical; that is driven by compassion, equity, and justice for communities rather than unbridled growth and scale; that is grounded in learning and adaptation with communities rather than silver bullets and donor priorities. </p>

<p>After years of engaging with more traditional models of leadership, I was recently exposed to a different methodology I believe has the potential to help us escape this cycle. In October 2021, I began the process of becoming an Integral Master Coach through Integral Coaching Canada. While I didn’t realize it when I began, this experience would add an additional dimension to what has been a lifelong investigation—spanning my careers as an urban development researcher, a professor, a philanthropy advisor, and a grantmaker.</p>

<p>Becoming an Integral Master Coach was intensive, exhausting, and—as is this case with many such experiences—deeply rewarding and transformative. It required that I take a long, hard look in the mirror, reflect, appreciate how I came to be who I am, and consider what beliefs and behaviours it was time to leave behind so I could embody new ways of being and working.  I learned about the close connection between personal transformation and doing transformative work, about the power of presence and deep listening, and how to support others to embark on their own personal transformation journey using a structured, integral developmental process.  Now I am going to draw from this methodology as I continue to work with civil society leaders across Africa who, despite playing a central role in bringing about the change we all wish to see, do not always receive the in-depth, context-specific support they need.</p>

<p>The Collective Rising Leadership Institute is piloting an approach to (re)connect leaders with their purpose, with their communities, and with each other. It aims to set individuals, leadership teams, and organizations on a developmental journey in which they reflect critically about their role as active brokers between communities—and their vision for the future—and the various actors who help make that vision a reality. In doing so, we hope to sow the seeds of a movement. In this movement, leaders are not only equipped with tactics and evidence, but they are also deeply self-aware and grounded in their self. They come together, listen and learn from communities, and collectively pursue transformative agendas that truly prioritize the wants and needs of the most marginalized. The program will work at multiple levels simultaneously—the individual, the leadership team, the organization, and the cohort.</p>

<p>Its three main components are: </p>

<ol>
  <li>Individual Awareness and Development </li>
  <li>Collective Awareness and Development through group coaching </li>
  <li>Cohort Building and Skill Development</li>
</ol>

<p>In October, I head home to East Africa to officially launch this new initiative with four organizations working across East Africa on quality, inclusive education, as well as leadership teams from the Regional Education Learning Initiative (RELI) Africa.  I will continue to share what we are discovering together as we go. There are no closed doors here. I have never stopped learning, and I know that I will continue to do so. Please get in touch if you are asking similar questions about what leadership models might be best suited to address and transform the complexities and realities in Africa. </p>

<p>My adventure continues! Please join me by following me on LinkedIn.</p>]]></content><author><name>Joyce Malombe</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After 11 years, I transitioned from my position as the Program Director of International Children’s Education at Wellspring Philanthropic Fund and began piloting a new initiative.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://auxilia.io/adventure/header-image" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://auxilia.io/adventure/header-image" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Update on Collective Rising Leadership Institute</title><link href="https://auxilia.io/articles/update-on-collective-rising-leadership-institute/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Update on Collective Rising Leadership Institute" /><published>2025-07-16T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-16T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://auxilia.io/articles/update-on-collective-rising-leadership-institute</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://auxilia.io/articles/update-on-collective-rising-leadership-institute/"><![CDATA[<p>Leadership was never meant to be a solo act. It’s a journey we’re meant to walk together — building, learning, and rising as one.</p>

<p>Across decades as a grantmaker, urban development researcher, professor, and now as a coach, I keep returning to the same question: Why do we keep focusing on individual leaders when real change in communities is collective?</p>

<p>In 2023, we launched the Collective Rising Leadership Institute and its first cohort of leaders not with answers, but with a set of questions to explore:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What becomes possible when leadership development isn’t about shaping individuals to lead alone, but about nurturing teams to grow together, connect to purpose, and spark change from within?</li>
  <li>How can leaders create meaningful change with and for the communities they serve?</li>
  <li>What would lasting change mean for the communities we seek to serve?</li>
</ul>

<p>Together with 35 education leaders from four organizations and two RELI country leadership networks across Kenya and Tanzania, we stepped into this experiment. We didn’t know what would unfold, but we trusted the impulse to explore a new way, together. These leaders came together as a cohort and engaged in big questions and explorations, together completing team coaching on leadership to better understand themselves, their organizations, and their communities.</p>

<p>How we designed the Collective Rising experience:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Individual Awareness: We began with personalized assessments for leaders. These assessments gave leaders a mirror to their strengths, blind spots, and opportunities for personal growth. With support from learning partners and coaches, participants built the self-awareness, self-trust, and empathy needed to lead differently.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Collective Awareness: Through integral team coaching, leaders shifted from “I” to “We.” They began to learn how to lead with one another, anchored in shared purpose and responsibility to the communities they serve. Together, they celebrated one another’s strengths and started a journey of evolving as a team.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Skill Building &amp; Cohort Connection: We introduced practical tools and practices around listening, communication, and relational leadership. An Immersion and a Celebration Summit deepened these lessons and built bonds across one another and across organizations.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>What resulted:</p>

<p>Over the first nine-month cohort, and every cohort since, we’ve watched individuals change in incredibly meaningful ways. Teams and organizations likewise shift their cultures and practices to ways that support wellbeing internally and externally within the community. Importantly, every person who has walked through a CRLI program emerges with a new, stronger network and a strengthened desire to create change with and for others.</p>

<p>What we’re learning: Leadership shifts when individuals gain self-awareness, but it transforms when teams reorient around purpose, share leadership, and embed collaboration into how they work every day.</p>

<p>To the coaches, partners, and the 35 leaders who stepped into the unknown with us: Thank you. To all of our 85 (and counting!) alumni, you’ve inspired us and helped us to grow with you. And, of course, I’ve grown through this process, too: I’m gaining the ability to grow past my perfectionism and to trust myself as a coach more fully.</p>

<p>Today, we’re on our third cohort of leaders, many of whom are focused on girls’ education. We’re still asking big questions, refining our coaching model, and learning from every interaction. We’re building and rebuilding our model of leadership coaching every day to ensure we’re helping every leader, team, and organization to become their best selves.</p>

<p>Testing something new is a humbling and gratifying experience. The process and the change are slower than you want, muddled by an intense desire for complexity and perfectionism. I’m proud of what we’ve built together and excited to keep sharing about Collective Rising Leadership Institute in the months ahead as we get ready to launch our new website, continue refining our gender empowerment and equity model, and distill complex learnings from all the data we’ve collected across these three cohorts. I’m more hopeful than ever that change is possible.</p>

<p>I’d love to hear from you:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Where are you being invited to shift from “I” to “We” in your life right now?</li>
  <li>What leadership assumptions are you working to let go of right now?</li>
  <li>How are you nurturing leadership within your team or organization?</li>
  <li>What questions are shaping your work right now?</li>
</ul>

<p>Until next time, let’s keep rising together.</p>]]></content><author><name>Joyce Malombe</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Leadership was never meant to be a solo act. It’s a journey we’re meant to walk together — building, learning, and rising as one.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://auxilia.io/update/header-image" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://auxilia.io/update/header-image" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>